fine okay hello everyone i'm kevin
gustola managing editor for
shadowproof.com and i'm very pleased to
be joined
by john kiriakou cia whistleblower
and um also a colleague who uh
is a contributor over at consortium news
thanks for joining us john
happy to do it kevin
so um as we as we get rolling here one
second
as we get rolling here let me begin by
asking you
just generally i mean what a day what an
extraordinary day
this decision uh and
such a turn i mean 95 of the ruling as
you're going through it
sounds horrid like we're just in for the
inevitable
um i i was following it in real time
but so other people were following what
reporters were putting out there who
were following the virtual
the virtual courtroom and then suddenly
it takes this turn where the judge is
taking seriously his mental and physical
health what's your reaction to the
outcome here
i i was shocked very pleasantly so but
shocked
uh one of the things that um that really
surprised me was that the judge said
that the u.s government had made its
case and i don't think that the u.s
government at all made its case i think
that she said that gratuitously
because the uk has something called the
official secrets act
which is even more onerous than the
espionage act
and uh she wanted to
send him back to the us but you know in
the end
it seems that um that uh
a cooler head is what ended up
prevailing
and uh and she she changed her mind
now one one important point i think is
that there
is a precedent for british courts
not sending prisoners back to the united
states
uh and it's specifically because of the
way the u.s
uses solitary confinement the the un
considers the us practice of solitary to
be a form of torture
the british courts have held that it is
a form of torture
and if somebody is is mentally or
emotionally fragile it's very very easy
to commit suicide in prisons
certainly at the federal level people
commit suicide in american prisons
every single day and so in the end
despite the swipes that she took
at julian and julian's supporters
and julian's actions in the end she did
the right thing
you you and i we go back as uh people
who have been following the
mass incarceration system in the united
states very closely
and it was remarkable to me that
uh you know basically the us government
had an open and shut case they could
have convinced this
if you if you read it you know assuming
that she's not just copying out here i
mean there's
there's different ways that you can look
at what the judge is doing i see
one theory out there that she's just
basically
using this as a way to not have to
engage
the charges and find against
any of the allegations that were put
forward by
the us government this is a this is a
nice thing because as you say there's a
precedent there's a precedent here
for the uk government not authorizing
extraditions to the us
because of how people would be abused in
the u.s prison system
um but you know it's just it's
remarkable i mean the thing
i wonder if you have any comment here on
the part of the ruling where
uh she basically recognizes that julian
assange would be held in special
administrative measures if he was
brought to the united states
and i think uh you know what's so
important about this
aspect is she ties the
fact that she believes he would be put
in sam's
to the statements that mike pompeo had
made
about wikileaks being a non-state
hostile intelligence agency so i think
so crucial
for her to draw that connection that his
treatment in a us
prison would be a direct result of how
the u.s government
views him yeah i i was actually quite
excited by that
and i have to conclude also kevin that
you know after so many of us have spent
the last
how many years talking and writing
about uh conditions inside these special
communications these uh
communications management units cmus uh
that that the judge actually took this
seriously
you know so many times we we talked
about
how because julian was not your
run-of-the-mill prisoner who was going
to go into
an american prison that uh that he would
be placed in
in solitary confinement he would be
placed in a cmu
in some god forsaken place like like
florence uh the adx in florence or the
communications management unit in in the
penitentiary at terre haute
that that whatever they decided to do
with him
it was going to be terrible it was going
to be a human rights violation
it was going to push the man over the
edge mentally
it was going to possibly lead to his
suicide you know we talked about it so
much and held these vigils every month
and
and wrote about it in in publications
all around the world i like to think
that she took some notice
and and like you said after that
outrageous statement by mike pompeo
that wikileaks is a is a non-state
intelligence uh
service that was just too much i also
wonder too
and and if you'll allow me to even ask a
question of you
i wonder to if there was any role that
the incoming biden administration
played here i wonder if if
prosecutors consulted biden people if
the british consulted biden people
like did does the does the biden
administration
want this thing to go away so it's
interesting that you'd see
say that let me just plug the uh panel
discussion i wrapped up with noam
chomsky and dan
ellsberg and marjorie cohn that the
assange defense committee
hosted because gnome actually says this
he says if you believe in conspiracy
you would think that the biden team
consulted with the judge because this is
perfect for them think about it it
holds everything that the biden
administration would want
and they don't have to prosecute julian
assange in order
to have a precedent in this decision by
the
judge that would be useful to the us
government going forward
so it almost doesn't matter and i've
also
been in in talking with some people
today
highlighting the irony of all of this of
people who have
constantly acted like oh
this is an exception to the rule julian
assange isn't really a journalist
this is very unique they wouldn't really
come after journalists
but think of it this way everyone who
treated this as like an anomaly
that julian assange isn't really
you know like them he's now got off
on a technicality and they're the ones
who are in trouble
they're the ones who are going to be
left in the future trying to figure out
how to protect themselves from being
targeted i mean what do you say to that
that's right that that's probably the
most dangerous development
in this whole odyssey and that is that
the mainstream media
print and broadcast failed to rally
around julian they
failed to support julian on their
editorial pages
and so here's julian getting off on a
technicality
and still there's a path
for american journalists at a-list
outlets
doing their job investigative journalism
national security reporting
who now face espionage act charges and
they have only themselves to blame
because they did not support julian in
the first place
yeah and you know i'm just imagining
what if they had been louder
what if some of these people who have
spoken up for julian assange in the last
two weeks because it was like
fashionable to do so
as the clamor for a pardon from trump
escalated
what if uh you know alan russ bridger
has been outspoken i give him credit but
the new york times put
their editorial in support of assange in
their newspaper within the last
month yeah not sooner so what if these
places
had been more vocal all along maybe
maybe the judge wouldn't have been you
know so concerned that she would
upset the national security agencies
if she rebutted the uh charges and
allegations that were put forward by the
prosecutors but it's clear to me that it
looks like she's looking for a kind of
loophole
because you know i've always treated her
as a kind of careerist she's concerned
about her future
but she also knows that she doesn't want
her name to be tied
to a destructive outcome i mean i think
she's
this is as much about her as it is about
julian assange vanessa barretzer
does not want her career to be followed
by the fact that julian assange came to
the united states and then killed
himself
in a u.s prison yeah so she doesn't care
about julian assange's health
she just cares that people might come
after her
and dislike her because julian assange
hurt himself
yeah i think you're i think you're right
you know and this is the
this is the thing about these these
civil servants be they
uh prosecutors or judges this is how
they get promoted
right prosecutors don't get promoted by
not prosecuting people
they they get promoted by prosecuting
people convicting them
or or forcing a plea and then getting
the longest possible sentence
well here's here's a judge who's working
in a country that has
draconian national security laws
and uh she's she's examining this
extradition request from another country
that has draconian national security
laws
so what does she want to do she she
wants to show that she's a team player
she's not trying to upset the apple cart
and declare the espionage act
and the and the official secrets act
null and void so she gives us this
long soliloquy on how
the the department of justice proved its
case
that julian did all these terrible
things he leaked all this classified
information
but for humanitarian reasons
he's not going to be extradited it
wasn't i agree with you it wasn't for
humanitarian reasons
she was she was able to say all the
right things
to ensure her career and then make it so
that he didn't come to the united states
and kill himself in a prison cell in the
end
everybody wins everybody wins
so just let me take a minute here i want
to read this
exceptional part which is that not only
is she finding he's going to be held
in sam's but that he would be sent to
adx florence and i i just want to take a
minute to read this section
um if you'll permit me i think it's
really important context for people
so that we get out here what it would be
like if julian assange
ended up or or if he had been authorized
to be sent to the u.s and was on this
path
to being held in adx florence this is
laid out in the center for
constitutional rights to report
and first off just let me take a moment
because it was
this this this man was a mentor of
julian assange let me just pay
tribute to michael ratner right now and
say you know how disappointed i
am that he can't be here to share in the
elation we're all feeling today
i know this is one of the people in
julian assange's life that he's been
greatly missing
but there's a report that the
constitutional rights worked on called
the darkest corner in 2017
and the judge quotes from it so i just
want people to be aware
if you don't know what sams are like at
adx florence it goes like this
prisoners are generally allowed a total
of 10 hours outside their cell per week
however the time is spent alone in a
small indoor room or a cage hardly
bigger than their cell
inmates are forbidden from communicating
with other prisoners
for example by yelling through the walls
communications with people outside the
prison
are usually restricted to their lawyers
in a few immediate family members
who must be cleared by the u.s
government sams typically restrict
prisoners
to writing one letter per week to a
single family member
and this may not exceed their three
double-sided sheets of paper
and they're forwarded to an fbi agent
for approval
over time the delays in receiving mail
can decr degrade the quality of
communication
between a prisoner and his family to the
point where it can feel worthless
phone calls are severely restricted and
contemporaneously monitored
during non-legal in-person visits
no physical contact is allowed with
conversations taking place through a
thick
glass barrier and prisoners shackled and
chained at their wrists
ankles and to the ground 14 days
notice 14 days advance notice required
for
visits and these can take months to
coordinate because
sam's prisoners cannot use a visiting
room
when any other prisoner is present
these are all of the things that she had
to factor
into her decision and i you know i asked
i'm talking to you you were sentenced to
prison for
30 months you weren't ever under any of
these
kinds of restrictions but you did have a
special designation you were treated
differently than some of the other
inmates at the low security prison so
you have some
experience with how you know people who
run the prison could treat you
differently
um i mean what do you have to say
to this pact because i'm really actually
stunned that she agreed he would be sent
to adx florence that was actually
uh highly debated during the extradition
trial
because there are other places he could
go there are other facilities but the
fact that she believes he can be sent to
one of the worst hellholes
in the united states that's pretty huge
it's huge uh that that is that is
the worst hellhole uh in the united
states at least
among federal prisons there was a
terrific expose
that was published in the new york times
magazine in may of
2015. i i remember it now five and a
half years later
because it was so impactful and it
talked about adx florence
and what it's like living there in
solitary confinement or in one of the
uh administrative the special
administrative units and
one prisoner and they they talked about
this prisoner because this was typical
of what prisoners experience at adx
florence
but one prisoner was so distraught at
not having
human contact with anybody that he
broke a window in his cell and he ate
the glass he ate the broken glass
just so that it would shred his stomach
so he could go to an outside hospital
and at least interact with another human
being
that's how bad things get now and when
they say that
you're allowed outside your cell for 10
hours a week
that's not exactly true what that means
is
at the back of the cell is a is a small
door and the door leads outside
to a cage and the cages are usually
about 10 feet by 10 feet
and so for one hour a day you can walk
in a circle
in that 10 foot by 10 foot enlarged
dog cage that's attached to the back of
your cell
so you're not really out of the cell per
se
you're just able to get a little bit of
fresh air for one hour
and then you're allowed two or three
times a week
out of the cell to take a shower and
that's it
um people who are in solitary
confinement are
are not permitted phone calls except to
their attorneys as you noted or as the
judge noted
uh you have to just like you see on tv
in the movies
if you have a visitor which is rare it's
behind that
that glass wall and you have to have a
phone and and talk to your visitor over
the phone
uh and then if you receive a letter you
don't physically
get a copy of the letter what they do is
there's a screen like a tv screen or a
monitor
that's attached to the ceiling and
they'll scan your letter
and you're allowed to look up at the
monitor at the ceiling
and they'll have it there for five
minutes
you read it in that five minutes and
then they take it away and they destroy
the letter
so it's enough to make the the most sane
person insane i i don't know how anybody
over the long term can survive something
like that and
let's face it julian was looking at 175
years in prison
nobody can survive a lifetime of that
the most charitable sort of view was
that he would be there for the rest of
his life
for about a 40-year sentence yes that um
thomas durkin's an attorney in chicago
um
who has done a lot of work on national
security and civil liberties cases and
he provided testimony and
you know one of the things that he
assessed was that it could be about
40 years if it wasn't a maximum sentence
and
even there he's a 50 year old man do we
think julian assange is going to live to
be 90 years old probably not in his
condition
i mean we just have to be realistic here
and so anytime in prison
more than 20 to 30 years is probably
a death sentence it's a death sentence
kevin you and i have had this
conversation uh several different times
but when i was in prison and again
this was a low security prison people
were dropping like flies
you know you've got cancer they give you
tylenol
you have uh emphysema you get a tylenol
or diabetes you get a tylenol half the
people in there are insane
um one of the psychologists told me that
85 percent of prisoners in american
federal prisons
have some sort of mental illness 85
percent
well people who are mentally ill
generally don't take a
very good care of themselves physically
as well
and then on top of that you're in a
prison where it's difficult to take care
of yourself physically
uh the food is not human grade food
we've also talked about that
uh it's very very carb heavy
so you're not eating healthy foods you
lack
medical care a lot of people have these
these chronic uh conditions and then you
die
and that's it so sure if the average
life expectancy in the united states is
what 78 for men and 81 for women
you're not making it to 78 in a federal
prison
you're just not and uh the other thing
is beyond the mental health i mean we
got
insight into the fact that he suffers
from osteoporosis and we could
uh you know could be bending over and
suffer a fracture
there's no way he's getting any
appropriate attention
from any one inside the prison to treat
that condition
well osteoporosis is one of those
conditions that is not treated
in in u.s prisons like they'll they'll
treat you
if you have um something
immediate you've got diabetes they will
give you insulin
you've got a heart condition they'll
give you heart medication
but something like osteoporosis they're
not going to treat
hepatitis c they don't treat
because it's very expensive so you just
have to
you just have to lump it um there was a
prisoner
in my housing unit who had a quite a
long
sentence and had hepatitis c and there
was a court ruling saying that
that the prison had to uh give him this
medication i think it was a thousand
dollars a month it was when it first
came out
and what they did is they just released
him they just let him go
here there you go we're not paying for
this so
they're not going to give you the
medications that you need and something
like
osteoporosis is going to take a a
toll over a long period of time and it's
going to make for a miserable life
if it's not treated uh so what's your
reaction to
um you know aside from this aspect which
we can
give kudos i suppose to the judge for
being on the right side aside from this
you know a lot a lot of the rest is
pretty horrible and i must probably
spend the rest of the week digging
through it
and and doing reports and and piecing
out what
i know from covering the extradition
trial is complete bunk
from the judge but one thing i know that
you could
uh react to because we've talked about
it is the fact that she accepted
based upon a cnn story from 2019 about
how
they fabricated some thing that was
laundered by
us government officials or nat sec
officials
about the embassy being used as an
election meddling
command center that they said the
embassy so she agreed that
the embassy might have been used for
this purpose by assange
and so the the spying operation which we
have all kinds of details about
could have been reasonable and what's
your reaction to this right
you know that was one of the first
things that i
that i thought of when i woke up this
morning and saw what the decision was
my thought was i wonder what she said
about the spying operation
and uh i was disappointed because
she should have condemned this buying
operation to me the spying operation
should have been enough to result in
julian's release in the first place
and she just didn't uh she didn't
address
it at least not in any substantive way
um i agree with you i
i'm outraged at the notion and this
this is considered to be unethical in
the united states
judges are not allowed to you know
google you
or look for articles about you that's
just forbidden
and she freely admitted that that's
exactly what she did
to help her decide this case i was
flabbergasted by it
it's an article that was given to her by
the prosecutors but it can hardly be
claimed to be
primary evidence i mean it's
it's just uh hey let's float this idea
that he might be
working for the russians out of the
ecuador embassy
meanwhile uh for those who don't know
about this article
there's been some good write-ups about
it at the gray zone i did my own
write-up about it
because these are the exact same
documents that el pais had
yes and they at least responsibly looked
at each other and went
you know we're not going to make up some
story about him working for the russians
what's important here is that this shows
evidence of his legal team being
targeted
by some private security outfit and we
don't really know
if the cia or the fbi is behind it but
we do know that
some private security contractors should
probably be
pursued for committing criminal acts
because they should not be doing this
agreed and i think we do have to assume
that it was the cia behind it um even
though
the fbi would have had primacy on this
case
uh the cia always has primacy overseas
and so it it likely would have been a
cia operation
oftentimes um and i think this
this is apropos julian's situation
oftentimes
it's uh more cost effective and it's
safer
to contract it out to a private firm the
cia does that all the time
i think that's what we saw here this was
this was essentially a cia operation
that was just
farmed out to bring in sheldon adelson
to help
can you imagine uh so
and it's actually not a really good
operation because he already has yacht
security
so you would have scratch your head and
say
well you just hired david morales for
yacht security but you already have this
so what is this person doing
like even people at the company weren't
sure what this was about because
like why does sheldon adelson need help
with his yacht security
this is very confusing so um
there's a couple things i want to ask
you before we leave uh and
and the broadcast i've got some really
nice people following
our conversation uh mexico
is offering up political asylum to
julian assange what do you think about
that
i was thrilled thrilled to see the
report uh you know
we'd have to wonder if if the pri is
is uh is elected again uh if if there
would be any impact on
on julian but i'll tell you what i was
really worried about
is that let's say julian wins this whole
thing the brits
expel him there was nowhere for him to
go so he goes back to australia he's an
australian citizen
what's to keep the united states from
then asking the australians to extradite
him
and he has to go through this whole
thing all over again so
when i saw that the mexicans had offered
him asylum i
i couldn't think of better news well the
other problem here is
that there are these allegations
outstanding that have nothing to do with
these 2010
offenses and i think the cloud hanging
over julian assange is going to be
what to do uh there's you know
it's very clear in this decision from
vanessa beretzer that she recognizes
the the authorities could come after him
for the vault seven materials
those are highly highly classified those
are like revealing the
crown jewels right of how the cia yes
cyber operations so
yeah i'm i think there is a reasonable
fear and i think that's going to be
difficult for
julian and his people to figure out what
to do
once this case ends because i think the
question becomes
does joe biden decide to pursue a case
on very different grounds
yeah i i think that's really a great
question remember
it was it was the obama biden
administration
that prosecuted almost three times as
many whistleblowers as all previous
presidents combined
uh so yeah i i don't think that joe
biden becoming president
is is any great help uh for julian
assange
um i'll say also i have to agree with
your assessment that
that it's going to be difficult for
julian to actually do something
for a living once this is over let's
let's say
he ends up in mexico in the next uh
three weeks or so
what does he do if he goes back to
wikileaks
he makes himself a target and you know
that the justice department is
is licking its chops over prosecuting
the vault seven leaks
i mean like you said these were the
crown jewels these are these are
probably the most sensitive intelligence
related documents that have
ever been leaked uh they're going to
want to scalp
for that leak besides just the the guy
who released
the information so i i i would
worry about julian and and his future
you know eventually the spotlight is
going to leave him he's uh he's got two
children now
he has a partner who's very loving and
supportive
and so he's going to want to get along
with his life we just don't know what
that looks like
yeah and you know i wouldn't fault him
if you want to just hang it up
and and having a family i i
uh i think that was probably part of his
consideration when he decided to
have children um and you know he
believed that he was going to be able to
get out of this embassy
because he didn't think that the obama
administration
and and they didn't think the trump
administration oh sorry he did not think
that the obama administration was going
to come after him anymore
and in 2017 with the way that trump had
been talking about him i think he
thought that he might be insulated
somewhat
right although it turned out to be wrong
it turned out that jeff sessions could
do what he wanted with the justice
department without donald trump getting
involved
um but let me just also put forward this
scenario because we've got
um on the other side of the globe we've
got people in australia that are
watching us talk so i think let's
conclude here which is
you know australia has grown pretty
hostile towards whistleblowers
and the publication of information so
you what if
uh he ends up going back to australia
with his family um because that's where
he was born
and then they just returned to pursuing
an extradition there
maybe they decide within the justice
department
and the biden administration we don't
want to deal with the uk government
because we got this issue about
our prisons and that's set president
let's try australia and see if they'll
let us get julian assange
to the united states um the
government there is i don't know if
you're familiar but i think his name is
david mcbride
who has done the the revealing of crimes
war crimes in afghanistan and he's
facing
quite a harsh prosecution yes so well
that could be a great place to turn to
to get julian assange
yeah that's why i was so happy about
mexico the australian government is
quite conservative
and even by conservative standards
they're very very conservative when it
comes to whistleblower issues
whistleblowers are not protected in
australia especially national security
whistleblowers this is something that
that several different ngos are working
on
um in in australia especially uh
blueprint for free speech
which does a lot of these whistleblower
uh legislative projects around the world
even though they're based in australia
they have a devil of a time trying to
convince australian politicians
that whistleblowers ought to be
protected so yeah i agree
if if i were julian i wouldn't want to
go to australia right now
i would try to get to mexico as quickly
as possible
yeah i mean i think he has more
his fortunes could actually be much
better if he was able to repair
his standing in ecuador than if he tried
to go to australia like personally i
think
you probably want to go find a place in
latin america
before you head to um australia
yeah i would be careful about the the
kind of governments but
uh i mean bolivia's done pretty well to
beat back the united states so maybe he
should go
um befriend eva morales and and and live
in bolivia
right uh so um all right well thank you
oh there's one more thing i
i'll close with just to see if you
recognized
the fact that chelsea manning featured
in the decision
i don't know if you saw this but so
she referred to her suicide attempt as a
reason why julian assange
should not be extradited to the united
states which i thought was just an
incredible thing for the united states
overzealousness against the source of
these documents
to to come back and bite them so
directly i mean if you think about it
they were already done with her
they had already succeeded in breaking
her and they said
let's bring her back let's bring her
back and let's try to get her and turn
her against julian assange and make her
testify
against this wikileaks founder and she
stood up to them
and then because she stood up to them
and then you know
was mentally abused again but
survived the judge is now referencing
that
in a case against the u.s government to
justify not extraditing julian assange i
mean it's just
i think it's wonderful and also it's a
tribute to chelsea manning because i do
think
that uh when all of said and done
there's really a lot that julian
owes and it's not that he has to do
anything for her it's just that like
she's really done a good job here of
being silent of saying nothing and just
letting this
happen without any kind of divide being
opened between her and julian assange
yeah you know i i said actually i think
i said it to you
at the time that that chelsea manning
was consistently underestimated
uh not just through her trial but when
she was being held
in contempt of court for refusing to
testify against julian before a grand
jury
she was far far tougher than the justice
department ever gave her credit for
being
so it is kind of poetic justice that it
comes back
uh to bite prosecutors i mean the only
thing that ever really gets them right
is their overzealousness and how
how how far the the u.s government
goes you know beyond it um you know it's
they they never know when to stop they
they always find a way
to be their own enemy so i know you have
to go
and um i want to wrap up here but just
as we as we conclude
um thank you everyone for following the
broadcast i want to thank you john
for joining again if you go to
consortium news you're you're still
doing coverage of
the bureau of prisons and uh the
inhumanities and cruel abuses inside of
the prison system which will remain
important to this appeal
um i mean i guess the last thing i can
say here on our way out of this
broadcast is
it's a very narrow appeal that the us is
able to file
but i'm going to enjoy every bit of it
and you know i'm gonna enjoy every bit
of it
because the u.s is gonna have to prove
that their prison system
isn't cruel and vile before a three
panel appeals court
in the united kingdom and i'm you know
i'm kind of in the mood right now where
i'm grabbing the popcorn to hear
whatever
they try to come up with and that maybe
it's hubris but i just kind of feel like
they're not going to
have an easy time coming up with
anything that's persuasive
i have to agree there's no defense of
this system
none so i i'm anxious to hear uh what
kind of tale they
try to spit all right everyone well
um as as we as we end um you can
subscribe to the shadowproof
channel on youtube and i encourage you
to do so um and until next time
thank you and i'll see you all around